export const GOVERNMENTA2009 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Government as a process or art of governing means",
A: "voting at general elections",
B: "orders of the judiciary and police",
C: "activities of political parties and pressure groups",
D: "activities for making and enforcing laws in a state",
answer: "D. activities for making and enforcing laws in a state",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Nazism was practised in",
A: "Britain under Churchill",
B: "the United States under Woodrow Wilson",
C: "Germany under Adolf Hitler",
D: "Span under General Franco",
answer: "C. Germany under Adolf Hitler",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. Government can be made responsible and accountable to its citizens through the following methods except",
A: "periodic change of government",
B: "demonstration",
C: "political education",
D: "public opinion",
answer: "B. demonstration (While demonstrations can express public dissatisfaction, they are not a consistent or structured mechanism for holding governments accountable.)",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. Fascism can best be defined as the",
A: "government of a state-controlled by a multi-party",
B: "system of government controlled by the armed forces",
C: "existence of a single party dictatorship with a life president",
D: "existence of an elected president for a fixed term",
answer: "C. existence of a single party dictatorship with a life president",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. Totalitarianism implies the control of government by",
A: "coalition parties",
B: "parties in succession",
C: "a few elite",
D: "a dictator",
answer: "D. a dictator",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following countries practised a totalitarian system of government before the Second World War?",
A: "Britain and France",
B: "Germany and Italy",
C: "The United States and Canada",
D: "Turkey and India",
answer: "B. Germany and Italy",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The subordinate class of people in the social hierarchy of a feudal system is the",
A: "lords",
B: "vassals",
C: "nobles",
D: "armed forces",
answer: "B. vassals",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. A common language is one of the attributes of a",
A: "government",
B: "society",
C: "nation",
D: "state",
answer: "C. nation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. The doctrine of the rule of law is credited to",
A: "J.J. Rousseau",
B: "John Locke",
C: "A.V.Dicey",
D: "Thomas Hobbes",
answer: "C. A.V.Dicey",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Equality before the law is a principle of",
A: "separation of powers",
B: "checks and balances",
C: "collective responsibility",
D: "rule of law",
answer: "D. rule of law",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following is a limitation to the doctrine of rule of law?",
A: "Diplomatic immunity",
B: "Private ownership of property",
C: "Rights of enlightened citizens",
D: "Political authority of the executive",
answer: "A. Diplomatic immunity",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Which of the following principles is emphasized among the three organs of government in a presidential system?",
A: "separation of powers",
B: "Centralization",
C: "Delegted legislation",
D: "Political participation",
answer: "A. separation of powers",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. The principle of checks and balances is aimed at",
A: "allowing for a fusion of powers among the organs of government",
B: "preventing any organ of government from performing its duties",
C: "allowing for total independence of the three organs of government",
D: "preventing any organ of government from becoming too powerful",
answer: "D. preventing any organ of government from becoming too powerful",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. A truly representative government is one that",
A: "resists freedom of movement",
B: "recognizes unlimited franchise",
C: "observes customs and traditions",
D: "allows devolution of governmental powers",
answer: "B. recognizes unlimited franchise (Ideally, in a representative government, all eligible citizens should have the right to vote.)",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Which of the following is not the main source of a constitution?",
A: "Judicial precedents",
B: "Legislative decisions",
C: "Previous constitutions",
D: "Public deliberations",
answer: "B. Legislative decisions (While legislation can influence a constitution, it's not a primary source.)",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. A constitution whose procedure for amendment is the same as that of making an ordinary law is referred to as",
A: "a unitary constitution",
B: "an unwritten constitution",
C: "a flexible constitution",
D: "a confederal constitution",
answer: "C. a flexible constitution",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. A system of government in which the head of state is elected for a fixed term of office is known as",
A: "republican",
B: "monarchical",
C: "confederal",
D: "federal",
answer: "A. republican",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. A governmental system where the head of state is distinct from the head of government is called",
A: "presidential",
B: "unitary",
C: "parliamentary",
D: "republican",
answer: "C. parliamentary",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The type of government that is headed by a king or queen is called",
A: "monarchical",
B: "federal",
C: "presidential",
D: "republican",
answer: "A. monarchical",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The principle which requires members of the executive to resign when a governmental proposal is defeated in the parliament is known as",
A: "delegated legislation",
B: "individual responsibility",
C: "devolutionary powers",
D: "collective responsibility",
answer: "D. collective responsibility",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following systems of government is more responsive to public opinion?",
A: "Oligarchy",
B: "Republicanism",
C: "Plutocracy",
D: "Monarchy",
answer: "B. Republicanism (In a true republic, the people have a greater voice in governance.)",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. A federal system of government is adopted in a state with",
A: "a single ethnic group",
B: "small population with a large expanse of land",
C: "weak economic base",
D: "marked inequalities among the component units",
answer: "D. marked inequalities among the component units",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. A system of government in which governmental positions are acquired through popular elections is known as",
A: "fascism",
B: "confederalism",
C: "monarchy",
D: "republicanism",
answer: "D. republicanism",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The head of the judicial arm of government is known as",
A: "Chief Justice",
B: "Attorney-General",
C: "a judge",
D: "an advocate",
answer: "A. Chief Justice",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The implementation of government policies is carried out by the",
A: "Legislature",
B: "Judiciary",
C: "Ombudsman",
D: "Executive",
answer: "D. Executive",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. A system whereby there is only one legislative chamber parliament is referred to as",
A: "unicameral legislature",
B: "confederal legislature",
C: "monarchical legislature",
D: "bi-cameral legislature",
answer: "A. unicameral legislature",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Citizenship can be acquired through",
A: "renouncement",
B: "repudiation",
C: "birth",
D: "reference",
answer: "C. birth",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Residing in an area for a specified period of years is one of the basic conditions to acquire citizenship through",
A: "marriage",
B: "honour",
C: "naturalization",
D: "birth",
answer: "C. naturalization",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Civil rights in a country are enjoyed by",
A: "citizens",
B: "aliens",
C: "prisoners",
D: "refugees",
answer: "A. citizens",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Vibrant opposition parties in parliament help to",
A: "threaten democracy",
B: "strengthen democracy",
C: "safeguard independence",
D: "protect sovereignty",
answer: "B. strengthen democracy",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. The practice of voting in absentia through an authorized representative is",
A: "bye-election",
B: "delegated election",
C: "voting by proxy",
D: "quota voting",
answer: "C. voting by proxy",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Which of the following is a function of an electoral commission?",
A: "Educating the public on economic policies",
B: "Registration of voters for the election",
C: "Sharing of political power among parties",
D: "Provision of essential services",
answer: "B. Registration of voters for the election",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. A feature of pressure groups is that members",
A: "oppose the government",
B: "are in the same labour union",
C: "do not believe in dialogue",
D: "have similar interests",
answer: "D. have similar interests",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Measuring public opinion becomes highly expensive when",
A: "a referendum is held",
B: "public opinion poll is conducted",
C: "public debates are held",
D: "mass media reports are evaluated",
answer: "B. public opinion poll",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. The non-involvement of civil servants in partisan politics is related to",
A: "anonymity",
B: "neutrality",
C: "permanence",
D: "impartiality",
answer: "B. neutrality",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. A court can declare any action of a local government that is outside its area of jurisdiction as",
A: "ultra vires",
B: "bill of rights",
C: "certiorari",
D: "habeas corpus",
answer: "A. ultra vires (Meaning 'beyond the powers')",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Laws made by the legislative council during the colonial period in British West Africa were called",
A: "acts of parliament",
B: "delegated legislations",
C: "ordinances",
D: "bye-laws",
answer: "C. ordinances",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. The French colonial policy of Assimilation was first applied in",
A: "Conakry, Goree, Bamako and St. Louis",
B: "Dakar, St, Louis, Goree and Conakry",
C: "Goree, Dakar, Bamako and Abidjan",
D: "St. Louis, Dakar, Goree and Rufisque",
answer: "D. St. Louis, Dakar, Goree and Rufisque",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. One of the criticisms against the policy of Assimilation was that it",
A: "did not recognise African culture as good enough",
B: "granted French citizenship to all the people in Senegal",
C: "ignored the educated elite",
D: "recognised the traditional rulers",
answer: "A. did not recognise African culture as good enough",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Nationalism in British West Africa aimed at",
A: "gaining independence",
B: "abolishing chieftaincy",
C: "collecting revenue",
D: "constructing roads",
answer: "A. gaining independence",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. One of the demerits of the pre-Second World War constitutions of West African colonies was the",
A: "domination of the Legislative Council by official members",
B: "domination of the Legislative Council by un-official members",
C: "introduction of indirect Rule system in the colonies",
D: "exclusion of traditional rulers from the government",
answer: "A. domination of the Legislative Council by official members",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. The first military coup détat in West Africa was staged in",
A: "The Gambia",
B: "Niger",
C: "Nigeria",
D: "Togo",
answer: "D. Togo",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Which of the following does not influence the foreign policy of a country?",
A: "Historical and cultural matters",
B: "Ideological factors",
C: "Economic factors",
D: "Intra-party conflicts",
answer: "D. Intra-party conflicts (While internal party issues can indirectly affect foreign policy, they are not a primary determinant.)",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The highest organ of the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) is the",
A: "Council of Ministers",
B: "Secretariat",
C: "Tribunal",
D: "Authority of Heads of State and Government",
answer: "D. Authority of Heads of State and Government",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the following countries is a founding member of the Commonwealth?",
A: "Zimbabwe",
B: "Ghana",
C: "India",
D: "South Africa",
answer: "C. India",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Which of the following African countries participated in the signing of the United Nations Organization (UNO) Charter in 1945?",
A: "Ethiopia",
B: "Tunisia",
C: "Ghana",
D: "Nigeria",
answer: "A. Ethiopia",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The Economic and Social Council of the United Nations Organization (UNO) is made up of",
A: "25 members",
B: "26 members",
C: "27 members",
D: "28 members",
answer: "C. 27 members",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. The Economic and Social Council of the United Nations Organization (UNO) is made up of",
A: "25 members",
B: "26 members",
C: "27 members",
D: "28 members",
answer: "C. 27 members",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. *******************************",
A: "*******************************",
B: "*******************************",
C: "*******************************",
D: "*******************************",
answer: "Z. zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
correctLetter: "Z",
correctOption: 9,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The United Nations Secretary-General is appointed for a",
A: "five-year term",
B: "four-year term",
C: "three-year term",
D: "single-year term",
answer: "A. five-year term",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]